Guide to Zevi Salsburg audio-visual collection UA 408
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Zevi Salsburg audio-visual collection
1950s-1970
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Salsburg, Zevi
UA 408
2090
1 Linear Feet 10 16mm films, 1 Super 8mm film, 1 audio reel
3.44 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0408aip_001
Collection of 10 16mm films, 1 Super 8mm film, 1 audio reel filmed by Dr. Zevi Salsburg in the 1950s-1970s. Films include family events, travel, and scenes at Rice University.
Biographical / Historical
Zevi W. Salsburg was professor of chemistry and mathematical science at Rice University from 1954 until his death in 1970. Salsburg earned his Ph.D in 1953 at Yale, where he was a member of the influential John Kirkwood group in statistical mechanics. He came to Rice in 1954 as a member of the Chemistry department, later holding an appointment in mathematical science as well. He published extensively in chemical physics, held fellowships from NSF, the National Research Council, and the Guggenheim Foundation, and consulted for both Los Alamos and the Lawrence Radiation Lab at Livermore. Salsburg was also a key contributor, as a fund-raiser and designer, of the R1 computer that was built by Rice faculty in Abercrombie Lab.
In 1956, three Rice University faculty members, Zevi Salsburg, John Kilpatrick, and Larry Biedenharn, brought supercomputing to the school for the first time in the form of the R1 computer. While it wasn't the first computer at Rice, it was the university's first large computational research computer.
Content Description
Collection of 10 16mm films, 1 Super 8mm film, 1 audio reel.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These films were given to the Woodson Research Center by Linda Salsburg Samuelson in 2014.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
digital moving image formats
Places
Rice University
- Series I. Films and audio recording (Box 1)
  - Salsburg film 001, 1959
    Scope and Contents
    Contains 16 mm film footage of Zevi Salsburg and wife on vacation in mountains, around Los Alamos, New Mexico, Summer 1959. Length of film 11:44 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 002, circa 1961-62
    Contains 16 mm film footage of Zevi Salsburg, family, children. Length of film 06:01 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 003, 1959
    Contains 16 mm film footage of Zevi Salsburg and his wife on train trip, views of moutain, Shalona Lake, Colorado and New Mexico in 1959. Length of film 11:34 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 004, 1957
    Contains 16 mm film footage of Zevi Salsburg visiting Yosemite, Rice campus, Europe in 1957. Length of film 07:39 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 005, 1958
    Contains 16 mm film footage of Labor Day activities and U.S. travel in 1958. Length of film 07:45 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 006
    16 mm film footage of Zevi Salsburg and Rosselini interview. Contains audio. Length of film 06:50 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 007
    Contains Super 8 film footage of two boys running on a track. Length of film 10:48 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 008, 1963
    16 mm film footage of Zevi Salsburg and family, Easter egg hunt at Rice University, beach, family gatherings. Length of film 16:12 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 009, 1950s
    Contains 16 mm film footage of vacation to Yosemite. Length of film 09:41 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 010
    16 mm film footage of Zevi Salsburg wedding shower, wedding, and reception. Length of film 12:59 minutes.
  - Salsburg film 011, 1961
    Contains 16 mm film footage of Salsburg family and trip to Memphis in 1961. Length of film is 14:01 mintues.
  - KTRU audio recording, 1970-04-11
    KTRU news special, Dr. Salsburg, member of Faculty, selected to go before Board of Governors on Friday, April 10, with resoution passed by special faculty meeting. Interviewed live by Pat Baum. Length of audio 15:10 minutes.